You know, we always think that hey, there are these idealized versions, people are just showing the best things that happened in their lives. I've thought that many times. My friends, no way they can be that cool and have good of a life. Well, one study tested this by examining people's personalities. They had four good friends of a person judge their personality. Then they had strangers, many strangers, judge the person's personality just from Facebook, and what they found was those judgments of the personality were pretty much identical, highly correlated, meaning that Facebook profiles really do reflect our actual personality. All right, well, what about online dating? I mean, that's a pretty deceptive space. I'm sure you all have "friends" that have used online dating. (Laughter) And they would tell you about that guy that had no hair when he came, or the woman that didn't look at all like her photo. Well, we were really interested in it, and so what we did is we brought people, online daters, into the lab, and then we measured them. We got their height up against the wall, we put them on a scale, got their weight -- ladies loved that -- and then we actually got their driver's license to get their age. And what we found was very, very interesting. Here's an example of the men and the height. Along the bottom is how tall they said they were in their profile. Along the y-axis, the vertical axis, is how tall they actually were. That diagonal line is the truth line. If their dot's on it, they were telling exactly the truth. Now, as you see, most of the little dots are below the line. What it means is all the guys were lying about their height. In fact, they lied about their height about nine tenths of an inch, what we say in the lab as "strong rounding up." (Laughter) You get to 5'8" and one tenth, and boom! 5'9". But what's really important here is, look at all those dots. They are clustering pretty close to the truth. What we found was 80 percent of our participants did indeed lie on one of those dimensions, but they always lied by a little bit. One of the reasons is pretty simple. If you go to a date, a coffee date, and you're completely different than what you said, game over. Right? So people lied frequently, but they lied subtly, not too much. They were constrained. Well, what explains all these studies? What explains the fact that despite our intuitions, mine included, a lot of online communication, technologically-mediated communication, is more honest than face to face? That really is strange. How do we explain this? Well, to do that, one thing is we can look at the deception-detection literature. It's a very old literature by now, it's coming up on 50 years. It's been reviewed many times. There's been thousands of trials, hundreds of studies, and there's some really compelling findings. The first is, we're really bad at detecting deception, really bad. Fifty-four percent accuracy on average when you have to tell if somebody that just said a statement is lying or not. That's really bad. Why is it so bad? Well it has to do with Pinocchio's nose. If I were to ask you guys, what do you rely on when you're looking at somebody and you want to find out if they're lying? What cue do you pay attention to? Most of you would say that one of the cues you look at is the eyes. The eyes are the window to the soul. And you're not alone. Around the world, almost every culture, one of the top cues is eyes. But the research over the last 50 years says there's actually no reliable cue to deception, which blew me away, and it's one of the hard lessons that I learned when I was customs officer. The eyes do not tell us whether somebody's lying or not. Some situations, yes -- high stakes, maybe their pupils dilate, their pitch goes up, their body movements change a little bit, but not all the time, not for everybody, it's not reliable. Strange. The other thing is that just because you can't see me doesn't mean I'm going to lie. It's common sense, but one important finding is that we lie for a reason. We lie to protect ourselves or for our own gain or for somebody else's gain. So there are some pathological liars, but they make up a tiny portion of the population. We lie for a reason. Just because people can't see us doesn't mean we're going to necessarily lie. But I think there's actually something much more interesting and fundamental going on here. The next big thing for me, the next big idea, we can find by going way back in history to the origins of language. Most linguists agree that we started speaking somewhere between 50,000 and 100,000 years ago. That's a long time ago. A lot of humans have lived since then. We've been talking, I guess, about fires and caves and saber-toothed tigers. I don't know what they talked about, but they were doing a lot of talking, and like I said, there's a lot of humans evolving speaking, about 100 billion people in fact. What's important though is that writing only emerged about 5,000 years ago. So what that means is that all the people before there was any writing, every word that they ever said, every utterance disappeared. No trace. Evanescent. Gone. So we've been evolving to talk in a way in which there is no record. In fact, even the next big change to writing was only 500 years ago now, with the printing press, which is very recent in our past, and literacy rates remained incredibly low right up until World War II, so even the people of the last two millennia, most of the words they ever said -- poof! -- disappeared. Let's turn to now, the networked age. How many of you have recorded something today? Anybody do any writing today? Did anybody write a word? It looks like almost every single person here recorded something. In this room, right now, we've probably recorded more than almost all of human pre-ancient history. That is crazy. We're entering this amazing period of flux in human evolution where we've evolved to speak in a way in which our words disappear, but we're in an environment where we're recording everything. In fact, I think in the very near future, it's not just what we write that will be recorded, everything we do will be recorded. What does that mean? What's the next big idea from that? Well, as a social scientist, this is the most amazing thing I have ever even dreamed of. Now, I can look at all those words that used to, for millennia, disappear. I can look at lies that before were said and then gone. You remember those Astroturfing reviews that we were talking about before? Well, when they write a fake review, they have to post it somewhere, and it's left behind for us. So one thing that we did, and I'll give you an example of looking at the language, is we paid people to write some fake reviews. One of these reviews is fake. The person never was at the James Hotel. The other review is real. The person stayed there. Now, your task now is to decide which review is fake? I'll give you a moment to read through them. But I want everybody to raise their hand at some point. Remember, I study deception. I can tell if you don't raise your hand. All right, how many of you believe that A is the fake? All right. Very good. About half. And how many of you think that B is? All right. Slightly more for B. Excellent. Here's the answer. B is a fake. Well done second group. You dominated the first group. (Laughter) You're actually a little bit unusual. Every time we demonstrate this, it's usually about a 50-50 split, which fits with the research, 54 percent. Maybe people here in Winnipeg are more suspicious and better at figuring it out. Those cold, hard winters, I love it. All right, so why do I care about this? Well, what I can do now with my colleagues in computer science is we can create computer algorithms that can analyze the linguistic traces of deception. Let me highlight a couple of things here in the fake review. The first is that liars tend to think about narrative. They make up a story: Who? And what happened? And that's what happened here. Our fake reviewers talked about who they were with and what they were doing. They also used the first person singular, I, way more than the people that actually stayed there. They were inserting themselves into the hotel review, kind of trying to convince you they were there. In contrast, the people that wrote the reviews that were actually there, their bodies actually entered the physical space, they talked a lot more about spatial information. They said how big the bathroom was, or they said, you know, here's how far shopping is from the hotel. Now, you guys did pretty well. Most people perform at chance at this task. Our computer algorithm is very accurate, much more accurate than humans can be, and it's not going to be accurate all the time. This isn't a deception-detection machine to tell if your girlfriend's lying to you on text messaging. We believe that every lie now, every type of lie -- fake hotel reviews, fake shoe reviews, your girlfriend cheating on you with text messaging -- those are all different lies. They're going to have different patterns of language. But because everything's recorded now, we can look at all of those kinds of lies. Now, as I said, as a social scientist, this is wonderful. It's transformational. We're going to be able to learn so much more about human thought and expression, about everything from love to attitudes, because everything is being recorded now, but what does it mean for the average citizen? What does it mean for us in our lives? Well, let's forget deception for a bit. One of the big ideas, I believe, is that we're leaving these huge traces behind. My outbox for email is massive, and I never look at it. I write all the time, but I never look at my record, at my trace. And I think we're going to see a lot more of that, where we can reflect on who we are by looking at what we wrote, what we said, what we did. Now, if we bring it back to deception, there's a couple of take-away things here. First, lying online can be very dangerous, right? Not only are you leaving a record for yourself on your machine, but you're leaving a record on the person that you were lying to, and you're also leaving them around for me to analyze with some computer algorithms. So by all means, go ahead and do that, that's good. But when it comes to lying and what we want to do with our lives, I think we can go back to Diogenes and Confucius. And they were less concerned about whether to lie or not to lie, and more concerned about being true to the self, and I think this is really important. Now, when you are about to say or do something, we can think, do I want this to be part of my legacy, part of my personal record? Because in the digital age we live in now, in the networked age, we are all leaving a record. Thank you so much for your time, and good luck with your record. (Applause)
Siempre pensamos que en estas versiones idealizadas, la gente muestra lo mejor que le ha pasado en su vida. Muchas veces he pensado así. Mis amigos, no pueden ser tan geniales y tener tan buena vida. Bien, un estudio probó esto examinando las personalidades de la gente. Cuatro buenos amigos del individuo debían juzgar su personalidad. Luego muchos desconocidos, tenían que juzgar su personalidad a través de Facebook, y lo que se descubrió fue que los juicios de la personalidad eran prácticamente idénticos, altamente correlacionados, lo que significa que los perfiles de Facebook realmente reflejan nuestra verdadera personalidad. Bien, ¿qué decir de las citas en línea? Es decir, es un ambiente que se presta bastante para el engaño. Estoy seguro de que todos Uds. tienen "amigos" que han utilizado citas en línea. (Risas) Y te deben haber contado del tipo que no tenía pelo cuando se presentó, o de la mujer que no se parecía en absoluto a su foto. Bien, esto nos interesaba realmente, así que trajimos personas que hacen citas en línea, al laboratorio, y luego los medimos. Tomamos su altura contra la pared, los pusimos en una balanza, obtuvimos su peso —a las señoras les encantó— y les pedimos la licencia de conducir para saber su edad. Y lo que descubrimos fue muy, muy interesante. Aquí hay un ejemplo de los hombres y la altura. En la parte inferior está la altura que ellos declararon en su perfil. En el eje vertical, tenemos la altura real. Esa línea diagonal es la línea de la verdad. Si el punto está sobre ella decían exactamente la verdad. Ahora, como pueden ver, la mayoría de los puntos está por debajo de la línea. Lo cual significa que todos los hombres han mentido sobre su altura. De hecho, mintieron sobre su altura en poco más de 2,3 cm, lo que en el laboratorio llamamos "fuerte redondeo hacia arriba". (Risas) Mides casi 1,73 m y ¡bum!, 1,75 m. Pero lo que es realmente importante aquí es, miren todos esos puntos. Se agrupan bastante cerca de la verdad. Lo que descubrimos fue que el 80% de nuestros participantes mintió sobre una de esas dimensiones, pero siempre mentían por poco. Una de las razones es bastante simple. Si acudes a una cita, a tomar un café y eres completamente diferente a lo que dijiste ser, se terminó ¿no? Entonces las personas mintieron con frecuencia, pero mintieron sutilmente, no demasiado. Se contuvieron. Bien, ¿qué explican todos estos estudios? ¿Cómo se explica el hecho de que a pesar de nuestra intuición, incluso la mía, mucha de la comunicación en línea, a través de un medio tecnológico, sea más honesta que la comunicación cara a cara? Es realmente extraño. ¿Cómo podemos explicar esto? Bueno, para ello, podemos observar la literatura de detección del engaño. Es una literatura muy antigua, surgió hace 50 años. Ha sido revisada varias veces. Ha habido miles de ensayos, cientos de estudios, y hay algunos resultados realmente convincentes. El primero es que somos bastante malos para la detección del engaño, realmente malos. 54% de exactitud, en promedio cuando se trata de decir si alguien que acaba de hacer una declaración está mintiendo o no. Eso es muy malo. ¿Por qué es tan malo? Bueno, tiene que ver con la nariz de Pinocho. Si les preguntara a Uds., ¿de qué fiarse cuando miran a alguien y quieren averiguar si está mintiendo? ¿A qué indicio deben prestar atención? La mayoría de Uds. diría que una señal a tener en cuenta son los ojos. Los ojos son la ventana del alma. Y Uds. no serían los únicos. En todo el mundo, en casi todas las culturas, una de las claves principales son los ojos. Pero la investigación durante los últimos 50 años, dice que no hay realmente ninguna señal confiable para detectar el engaño, lo que me ha sorprendido, y es una de las duras lecciones que aprendí cuando era funcionario de aduana. Los ojos no nos dicen si alguien está mintiendo o no. En algunas situaciones, sí, cuando el riesgo es alto, tal vez las pupilas se dilaten, el tono de voz sube y los movimientos corporales cambien un poco, pero no siempre, ni para todos. No es algo confiable. Extraño. Además solo porque no puedas verme no significa que voy a mentir. Es de sentido común, pero un hallazgo importante es que mentimos por alguna razón. Mentimos para protegernos, en nuestro propio beneficio o en el de alguien más. Hay mentirosos patológicos, pero representan una pequeña parte de la población. Mentimos por alguna razón. El hecho de que la gente no pueda vernos no significa necesariamente que vayamos a mentir. Pero creo que en realidad hay algo mucho más interesante y fundamental que pasa aquí. La próxima gran idea, podemos encontrarla yendo atrás en la historia hasta los orígenes del lenguaje. La mayoría de los lingüistas coincide en que empezamos a hablar en alguna parte entre 50 000 y 100 000 años atrás. Eso es mucho tiempo. Gran cantidad de seres humanos ha vivido desde entonces. Hemos estado hablando, me imagino, sobre fuegos, cuevas y tigres dientes de sable. No sé de qué hablaban, pero hablaban mucho, y como he dicho, fue enorme la cantidad de seres humanos que hizo evolucionar el habla, alrededor de 100 mil millones de personas. Lo importante sin embargo es que la escritura solo surgió hace unos 5000 años. Lo cual significa que todas las personas anteriores a la aparición de la escritura, cada palabra que hayan dicho, toda expresión, desapareció. Sin rastro. Se evanesció. Se fue. Así que hemos evolucionado para hablar de una manera en la que no hay registro. De hecho, el siguiente gran cambio a la escritura se produjo hace solo 500 años, con la imprenta, que es bastante reciente en nuestro pasado, y las tasas de alfabetización permanecieron muy bajas hasta la Segunda Guerra Mundial, por lo que incluso la gente de los dos últimos milenios, la mayoría de las palabras que han dicho - ¡puf! - desaparecieron. Pasemos al presente, la era de Internet. ¿Cuántos de Uds. han grabado algo hoy? ¿Alguien ha escrito algo hoy? ¿Alguien escribió alguna palabra? Parece que casi todos aquí han grabado algo. En esta sala, ahora mismo, probablemente hemos registrado más que casi toda la prehistoria de la humanidad. Es una locura. Estamos entrando en un período increíble de cambio continuo en la evolución humana por el que hemos pasado de hablar de una manera en que nuestras palabras desaparecen, a un entorno en el que estamos grabando todo. De hecho, creo que en un futuro muy próximo, no solo se grabará lo que escribimos, todo lo que hacemos será registrado. ¿Qué significa eso? ¿Cuál es la próxima gran idea? Bien, como científico social, esto es lo más asombroso que ni siquiera he soñado. Ahora, puedo mirar a todas estas palabras que durante milenios desaparecieron. Puedo observar las mentiras que primero fueron dichas y luego desaparecieron. ¿Recuerdan esos comentarios de "astroturfing" de los que hablamos antes? Bueno, cuando se escribe una reseña falsa, tiene que publicarse en algún lugar, quedando a nuestra disposición. Algo que hicimos y les daré un ejemplo en relación con el habla, es que le pagamos a la gente para escribir algunas opiniones falsas. Uno de estos comentarios es falso. La persona nunca estuvo en el Hotel James. El otro comentario es real. La persona estuvo allí. Ahora, la tarea de Uds. es decidir cuál de ellos es falso. Les daré un momento para leerlos. Pero quiero que levanten la mano en determinado momento. Recuerden, yo estudio el engaño. Me daré cuenta si no levantan la mano. Bien, ¿cuántos de Uds. creen que "A" es el comentario falso? Muy bien. Muy bien. Aproximadamente la mitad. Y ¿cuántos de Uds. piensan que "B" lo es? Muy bien. Un poco más para "B". Excelente. Aquí está la respuesta. "B" es el falso. Bien hecho segundo grupo. Le ganaron al primer grupo. (Risas) En realidad es un poco inusual. Cada vez que hacemos esta demostración, normalmente la división es de 50-50, lo cual concuerda con la investigación, 54%. Tal vez la gente aquí en Winnipeg sea más suspicaz y más hábil para darse cuenta. Esos inviernos fríos, rigurosos, me encantan. Muy bien, ¿por qué me interesa esto? Bueno, con mis colegas informáticos creamos algoritmos que analizan las huellas lingüísticas del engaño. Permítanme destacar un par de cosas sobre el comentario falso. La primera es que los mentirosos ponen el foco en la narrativa. Inventan un relato: ¿Quién? ¿Y qué pasó? Y eso fue lo que pasó aquí. Nuestros falsos opinadores contaron con quién estaban y lo que estaban haciendo. También utilizaban la primera persona del singular, "yo", en mayor medida que las personas que realmente estuvieron allí. Fueron introduciéndose en los comentarios sobre el hotel, como tratando de convencerte de que estuvieron allí. Por el contrario, la gente que dejó comentarios habiendo estado realmente allí, los que en realidad ingresaron en el espacio físico, dieron mucha más información referida al espacio. Dijeron de qué tamaño era el baño, o la distancia a la que estaba el centro comercial. Ahora, Uds. lo hicieron bastante bien. La mayoría prueban suerte con esta tarea. Nuestro algoritmo es muy preciso, mucho más preciso que los seres humanos, pero no siempre lo será. No se trata de un detector de mentiras que dice si tu novia te está mintiendo en los mensajes de texto. Creemos que la mentira, cualquier tipo de mentira —opiniones falsas de hoteles, de calzados, de tu novia engañándote con mensajes de texto— son mentiras diferentes. Van a tener diferentes patrones de lenguaje. Pero como ahora todo queda registrado, podemos analizar esas mentiras. Como he dicho, como científico social, esto es una maravilla. Es transformacional. Seremos capaces de aprender mucho más sobre el pensamiento humano y la expresión, sobre cualquier materia desde el amor a las actitudes, porque ahora todo se registra, pero, ¿qué significado tiene para el ciudadano común? ¿Qué significa en nuestras vidas? Bueno, dejemos un poco de lado el engaño. Una de las grandes ideas, creo, es que estamos dejando enormes rastros detrás nuestro. Mi buzón de salida de correo electrónico es enorme, y nunca me fijo. Escribo todo el tiempo, pero nunca me fijo en los rastros que quedan. Y creo que vamos a ver mucho más de eso, en que podamos reflexionar sobre quiénes somos mirando lo que escribimos, lo que dijimos, lo que hicimos. Ahora, volviendo al tema del engaño, hay un par de cosas para resaltar. En primer lugar, mentir en línea puede ser muy peligroso, ¿verdad? No solo queda un registro de ti mismo en tu máquina, también estás dejando un registro en la persona a quien le estabas mintiendo y además los estás dejando para que yo los analice con algunos algoritmos de computación. Así que por supuesto, sigue adelante y hazlo, está bien. Pero cuando se trata de la mentira y lo que queremos hacer con nuestras vidas, creo que podemos volver a Diógenes y Confucio. Estaban menos preocupados sobre mentir o no mentir y más preocupados por el ser fiel a sí mismo, y creo que esto es realmente importante. Ahora, cuando estén a punto de decir o hacer algo, podemos pensar, "¿quiero que esto sea parte de mi legado, de mi expediente personal?" Porque en la era digital que vivimos ahora, en la era de la red, todos estamos dejando un registro. Muchas gracias por su tiempo, y buena suerte con su registro. (Aplausos)